And one of them was Cabernet Soon. It's
a very premium Cabernet Sovio. And he
named it Don Maji. Why?
[Music]
So
in 1978, my father decided to plant
Cabernet Suon in the Barbaresco area.
Why? Why Cabernet? Because first he
wanted to show the greatness of the
territory of the land. He wanted to show
that this was the election territory for
the production of nei. But it was a
territory also that can be suitable for
the production of other varieties and
can show its creatance through other
varieties. The problem was that
his father so my grandfather Jovanni
>> was a believer in a buro. For him the
color of the wine in Pedmont was red
period.
>> You just mentioned earlier he's very
very traditional
you know the piamont or barrescoentric
and everything is about nebio
everything's aboutco you know so he's
very traditional.
>> Yeah very traditional your grandfather
>> he never considered white for him it was
only nebio so you can imagine how he
would have taken the news of planting
cab. So my father knew that he would
have never approved.
Still uh there was this uh beautiful
vineyard uh that previously was Nebulo
and is a vineyard where today Dmaji is
planted which was a a vineyard that is
in it's in the center of Barbaresco on
the on the central hill of Barbaresco
and it was a vineyard located just below
the house where my grandfather used to
live. So every morning when my
grandfather was waking up, he was
opening the windows of his bedroom and
he had this beautiful view on this
wonderful vineyard of the viol. So um my
father waited for it was winter of uh
1978.
He waited for my grandfather to go on
vacation.
>> Okay.
>> And my grandfather left for around two
weeks. And when he was gone, he called
the the vineyard manager and said,
"Take, you know, that vineyard of Nebolo
in the central barbaresco under Joanni's
house, take it away, replant it with
with the Cabernet vineard." So after two
weeks when my grandfather returned home,
was doing the road to go up to his house
and he sees that this vineyard magically
disappeared.
>> Oh my god.
>> So he called the vineyard manager and
said angry. What did you do? And the BM
manager said, "Look, this is not my
fault. This is your son that told me to
take away nebola and plant it with
cabin." And when my grandfather heard
the news, he did like this dharmi, which
means what a shame. Dharmmagi is a
pigment is a word. It's very similar to
French. In French is a dom. So dharmagi
is a pigment is for what a shame.
>> What a shame.
>> Okay, I see. So for you are if next time
you do something similar just make sure
to remind your father about this story
between him and his father.
>> Yeah I mean with with my father both me
and my sisters G Rosana we haven't
reached a Dharmmachi point yet at least.
>> Not yet. But regardless, Dharmaji
Cabernet Sovium proved to the world that
that Gaia will is able to the land and
your family is able to produce
international grape varietal that stands
in the best Cabernet of the world.
>> It's Yes, I I I agree. And it was also a
way to create more interest on Nebulo
because when my father started to travel
in the 1970s,
>> nobody knew Nebio. Nobody understood
nebulo because also it was a nebulo
different from today. Today I think
nebulo is changing into more flexible
variety something you can start to
approach also at a earlier stage. Back
then it was a lot of acidity a lot of
tins very harsh expression. So it was
very difficult to drink young. So when
people were drinking dharmi
or gay or or brasa so they knew that
they were international varieties. They
knew more or less what to expect
>> but then they had to discover where the
wine was coming from. So they had to
discover that it was coming from
Barbaresco that in Barbarco the the most
planted variety is nebio that nebio is
used to make Barbaresco in Bolo wine. So
it was a way also to fuel the interest
on Nebolo and the Barbaresco region.
Well, uh, for Barbresco, since I know
that actually just I would like to to
remind or to clarify to the fans of Gaia
that actually Gaia is that the heart of
Gaia is from Barbaresco. Yeah. So, so,
uh, Barbaresco and Barbaresco you have
three single vineyards and you have the
Barbaresco, uh, DOC. Yeah.
>> So, um, what's the difference? I mean,
so, so, um, the single vineyard, I know
that they're from single vineyard, but
how about the Barbaresco, which is the
the the not the flag, yes, the core. The
Barbaresco for us is the flagship wine
of the winery. It's a the only wine that
has always been produced for more than
160 years and that every single
generation has always been focusing on.
So the Barbaresco is the wine we are
known for and the wine that truly
represents who we are. The Barbaresco
for us is a blend of 14 different
vineyards of the Vo. 11 of these
vineyards are located in the Barbaresco
village. Three they come from the
village of TSO which is always part of
the Barbaresco
uh denomination.
The secret behind the the Barbaresco is
the diversity because the the 14
vineyards are completely different from
each other in terms of soil exposure,
exposition,
uh soil components. So they're
completely different, but when you blend
them together, uh they become
complimentary and each one helps the
other one.
>> A little contribution to your style.
>> Exactly. And so all together Exactly.
They create complexity and then and they
give you that.
>> All right, Joani, we've been talking
about Barbresco so much. Why don't we
have a drink?
>> Drinking that one.
>> Yes, please.
>> Yes.
>> Cheers.
>> Cheers. Thank you.
>> Very, very ele.
I know. Isn't it great?
>> This is what you can put it with
omelette. I'm just kidding. But anyway,
um I know that not every year you just
mentioned that that you produce this the
single year. So what happened to the
year that you don't produce the single
year?
>> So
>> what happened to the grapes? For
example, we have uh two examples 2018
and 2019 vintages. Uh both years we
decided to skip the production of solar
and Costarus. So in 2018,
the reason was that we had a big hail
storm that affected mostly the Barbaris
area. It's around 30 actors in the
center of Barbaresco. And in 2018, we
had part of the vineyard that usually go
into the production of the Barbaresco,
they were damaged by Ha. Mhm. and also
Sol San Lorenzo was damaged by it
because Soreno is really it's in the
center of Barbaro. So in 2018
we made a decision to make a selection
out of the 14 usual vineyards they go
into the Barbaresco we selected six and
then to this six to help the Barbarco we
added Costa Rusi and
because they were they actually were in
perfect conditions. There are still uh
grape sponges that are still present,
right?
>> Yeah. Well, Surin and Karusi were
actually not really affected by this
hail because they are located a little
bit outside of the village of Barbaro.
So, they were not affected by hail. So,
we decided to use Cost and we blended
them together in the Barbaris 2018
Sanoro was not used because it was
damaged. So, also
They are a trinity. They always go
together. It has never happened since
the first year of production that one
came out and the other two no or one out
of three or two out of three. They
either come out all the three or none of
them comes out.
>> Okay. And then in 2019
also we did something similar because
the hail that affected us in 2018 was
very violent
and it did not affect damaged only the
grapes but it damaged also some of the
gems that were supposed to give
production for the next year. So some of
the vineyards that we use for the
barbaresco even in 2019 were very
unbalanced. And so even in 2019 we
decided to make a selection of the
vineyards and then we added
and cost.
>> Wow. So see this is this is really being
responsible not only responsible but
pushing for perfection. So actually for
the fans of Gaia don't worry about good
vintages or bad vintages. In good
vintages you will be able to enjoy the
single vineyards but just so happens
that that there might be a lesser
vintage but the barresco will be
incredible because it will be joined
within it will be joined by the single
vineyards and the best vineyards of of
of Gaia which is the three story tilden
story San Lorenzo and uh you know so I
think this is very very interesting and
it's very important for for for the the
lover of Gaia to to know about it that
is great and Previously you also already
mentioned about how your father is
expanding into different parts of Italy
and uh why not abroad for your father
not for for your father why Italy only
so far that's tough question
um well in 1985
[Music]
I think I have the right my father did
have an opportunity to uh create
something together with Robert Mandari
He always had a beautiful friendship
with Robert. I think Robert influenced a
lot my father and there was actually
mutual estimation from uh from both side
and uh at the moment I think he was not
uh ready.
>> Mhm. I think uh my father has few
regrets in his life but that is probably
one of the few okay that if you ask him
today would tell you that it was it was
a mistake but you know after that in
1985 he he was not ready also
Gaia was still at the time in 1985 only
focused on Barbaru we didn't even have
Baro because then my father bought a
property in the heart of the Bolo in
1988. Then 1996 he developed um Conta
which is our single vineyard from
Lamora. uh but after that experience
after a few years in the middle of the
1990s then he expanded in well expanded
I don't I don't I don't like he he
broadened our horizons in
Kant in Montalcino and then Kamaranda
also at that time neither myself or my
two sisters a guy or Rossana were
involved in in the winery so it was
probably was not the right time to to do
it I was born in 1993
And then my father felt felt hope for
the future.
>> And then in 1994 and 1996 he moved to to
Daryus.
>> So I think there's a time for
everything. Yes. And probably at that
time he was not uh he was not ready but
>> but I think it's not it's not bad.
>> I think it's a beautiful mistake. It's
actually not a mistake. I think it's he
might regret at that time but
>> but actually it turned out to be even
better
>> you know and expand it's it's incredible
winery that your family you and your
family has created in in in Bologay and
Brunell
>> then suddenly why all the way to Sicily
and yeah in 2017 we we developed the new
project in Sicily
>> IDA that southwestern local Vietna
volcano
>> we're very excited because also is the
first partnership that we have done in
our history because it's a partnership
with the Grai family Alberto and Alena
Graach. Alberto is a winer located in
the northern slope of Etna called
Graach. Um and together we decided to
focus in the southwestern slope of
Edna is the tallest volcano of Europe
active volcano. There are
>> active volcano
>> 50 eruptions around 50 eruptions per
year. So what happened if if that 50 a
year?
>> Well,
>> so it's will it will it affect the the
the
>> in the last 250 years all the eruptions
are focused on the southwest sorry on
the western slope of ETA.
>> Okay.
>> Where is the only slope at the moment
where you don't have
production of of vineyards cuz the
vineyards are north, east and south.
>> So the the the soils is extremely
complex because of the eruption.
>> Yeah. Well, on the West End slope, yeah,
at the moment you don't have production
because all all the lava flows comes
down. We hope that for the next 250
years, it's going to stay like that.
>> But, you know, telling a volcano what to
do is not always the the easiest thing.
Yeah.
>> And so Angelo met Alberto in 2016
>> and
it was love at first sight because there
was a sharing of beliefs of values of
vision and together we decided to create
this new project on
>> Well, how about you? Your father I mean
you're the fifth generation. Your
father, how old is Angela? Your father?
>> 84.
>> 84. So, it's really up to you and your
sister, you know. So, um he'll still be
very healthy, very active. I'm sure
about that.
>> He's still incredibly active,
>> still very feisty,
>> you know, but but I think how about you?
What do you have in your mind and uh you
know that you you know you're you're not
plan I think plan is a little too
serious
>> I mean
>> but what what is in your heart or what
is in
>> so at the moment we have two new
wineries brand new uh we have a in
Sicily the new project in Atalanga so at
the moment we're focusing a lot in
giving these two project our full
dedication and full uh time to develop
them gradually and consistently.
The future uh
>> the future is the future.
>> The future is the future. We are very
positive about the future. I think uh we
have we still have a lot that we can uh
uh express from each of our wineries and
then maybe it always depends on
opportunity. If the right opportunity
comes then uh we will be happy to to
consider that. For me, my my dream would
be very interesting
to find
a new area maybe outside of Italy where
we could explore the potential of Nebul.
>> Okay. Oh, because Nebulo
>> that would be interesting.
>> Nebio is a very
little princess
>> because it's a variety that requires a
lot of patient, passion to to cultivate.
You need to have the right soils and in
the soil you need to have a good amount
of clay but not too much limestone but
again not too much. Everything needs to
be everything in balance. It's not easy
uh because it's difficult to find other
wine regions outside of Barian
Barbaresco where Nebio could give the
results that could be similar to the
original expression. But it's a dream
and maybe one day will come true. Yeah,
it's it's I think it's possible and and
I think that actually I didn't thought
about that because most most of the uh
the family the renowned family when they
go abroad they would always uh uh adopt
or plant the the the current great
varietal that is at that area.
>> Yeah.
>> But it's actually very very interesting
um and innovative
>> to to bring Nebulo outside.
>> It's it's very ambitious. This is very
challenging because nebolo is not called
an indigenous variety for nothing
>> cuz it's really connected to the
characteristics climatic conditions and
soil condition that we have in
Barbaresco or in the Lang region. So
>> it will be I think very difficult but
again maybe it will come true. I don't I
I'm I'm sure along the way you will make
little regrets or little mistake like
your father, but at the end I think with
what you just told me, I I I truly
believe that that that the dream will
come true and I I wait, you know, maybe
maybe my son will will be very happy to
see that, too. He's still in college
now, but and and one is still in high
school, but but sooner or later I'm I'm
sure it's going to be uh very good and
and it's very innovative. So, I'm going
[Music]
here to Taiwan and also to be able to
reveal so really the truth from the
bottom of the heart. Uh we call it the
heart and the soul and share with the
fans of Gala and and the wine lover.
>> Thank you. Thank you. I don't need a lot
of convincing to come to Taiwan. Thank
you so much. Thank you.
[Music]
Thank you. Cheers. Thank you. Cheers.
Cheers. Cheers everyone.
[Music]